A Guide to the Donald M. Sweig Manuscript Papers on “Registrations of Free Negroes”, 1976-1977
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Donald M. Sweig Manuscript Papers on “Registrations of Free Negroes”, 1976-1977
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 08-11
.25 linear feet
The Donald M. Sweig Manuscript Papers on "Registration of Free Negroes" consists of .25 linear feet spanning the years 1976-1977 and consisting entirely of photocopies of original archival material of registrations of free African-Americans in Fairfax County and Fredericksburg, Virginia from 1790-1862. Subjects include African American history; emancipation; and court records in Fairfax County and Fredericksburg, Va.
Sweig, Donald M. (1941 -)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Gift of Fairfax County Office of Comprehensive Planning
Historical and Biographical Information
Donald M. Sweig was born in Arlington, Va. and graduated from William and Mary with a B. A. in 1973, M.A. from George Mason in 1975, and a Ph.D. in History from William and Mary in 1982. He was a historian for Fairfax County, Va. for 27 years from 1975 - 2002.
In January 1974 two long lost volumes of Registrations of Free Negroes, Volume II (1822-1835) and Volume III (1835-1861) were discovered in the attic of the Fairfax County Courthouse. Volume I has never been found. Sweig photocopied the volumes to insure against loss or damage and went on to transcribe, edit and index them in 1976. In July 1977 Fairfax County published the completed manuscript under the title “Registrations of free Negroes: commencing September court 1822, book no.2 and Register of free Blacks 1835, book 3: Being the full text of the two extant volumes, 1822-1861, of registrations of free blacks now in the County Courthouse, Fairfax, Virginia”.
Scope and Content
The Donald M. Sweig Manuscript Papers on "Registration of Free Negroes" consists of .25 linear feet spanning the years 1976-1977 and consisting entirely of photocopies of original archival material of registrations of free African-Americans in Fairfax County and Fredericksburg, Virginia from 1790-1862. Sweig used the Fairfax County materials as sources for the book "Registrations of free Negroes: commencing September court 1822, book no.2 and Register of free Blacks 1835, book 3: Being the full text of the two extant volumes, 1822-1861, of registrations of free blacks now in the County Courthouse, Fairfax, Virginia" published in 1977. The "Certificates and Registry of Free Negroes. City of Fredericksburg, Va. 1790-1862" are copied from original records in the Fredericksburg Court House and includes a typed compiled index. Subjects include African American history; emancipation; and court records in Fairfax County and Fredericksburg, Va.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
The original registration documents are located in the papers of the Fairfax Circuit Court Historic Records Center, Fairfax, Va. and Fredericksburg Circuit Court, Fredericksburg, Va.
Donald M. Sweig Papers, 1976-1990, Special Collections Research Center, College of William and Mary
None
Index Terms
African Americans - Virginia - Fairfax County; African Americans - Virginia - Fredericksburg; Court records- Virginia - Fairfax County; Court records- Virginia - Fredericksburg; Fairfax County (Va.) - Genealogy - Sources; Slaves -- Emancipation -- Virginia - Fairfax County; Slaves -- Emancipation -- Virginia - Fredericksburg
Container List
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 2, 1822-1826 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 2, 1826-1835 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 2, 1830-1836 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 2, 1831-1835 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 3, 1831-1835 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 3, 1834-1840 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 3, 1841-1847 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 3, 1847-1850 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 3, 1850-1853 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Registrations of Free Negroes. Register No. 3, 1853-1861 [Photocopy], 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Certificates and Registry of Free Negroes. City of Fredericksburg, Va. 1790-1862 [Photocopy], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)